欢迎来到第六课！Welcome for our 6th tutorial !

这节课我们将学习如何通过鼠标和键盘来移动摄像机，感觉就像在第一人称射击游戏中一样。We will now learn how to use the mouse and the keyboard to move the camera just like in a FPS.
<h1>接口The interface</h1>
这段代码在整个课程中多次被使用，因此把它单独放在一个文件中：common/controls.cpp，然后在common/controls.hpp中声明接口函数，这样tutorial06.cpp就能使用它们了。Since this code will be re-used throughout the tutorials, we will put the code in a separate file : common/controls.cpp, and declare the functions in common/controls.hpp so that tutorial06.cpp knows about them.

tutorial06.cpp里的代码变动很小。主要的变化是需要每一帧都计算MVP矩阵，而不是像之前那样只计算一次。现在把这段代码加到主循环中：
The code of tutorial06.cpp doesn't change much from the previous tutorial. The major modification is that instead of computing the MVP matrix once, we now have to do it every frame. So let's move this code inside the main loop :
<pre class="brush: cpp">do{

    // ...

    // Compute the MVP matrix from keyboard and mouse input
    computeMatricesFromInputs();
    glm::mat4 ProjectionMatrix = getProjectionMatrix();
    glm::mat4 ViewMatrix = getViewMatrix();
    glm::mat4 ModelMatrix = glm::mat4(1.0);
    glm::mat4 MVP = ProjectionMatrix * ViewMatrix * ModelMatrix;

    // ...
}</pre>
这段代码需要3个新函数：
This code needs 3 new functions :
<ul>
	<li>computeMatricesFromInputs()是读入键盘和鼠标操作，然后计算投影和视图矩阵。这是奇妙所在处。computeMatricesFromInputs() reads the keyboard and mouse and computes the Projection and View matrices. This is where all the magic happens.</li>
	<li>getProjectionMatrix()返回已计算的投影矩阵。getProjectionMatrix() just returns the computed Projection matrix.</li>
	<li>getViewMatrix()返回已计算的视图矩阵。getViewMatrix() just returns the computed View matrix.</li>
</ul>
这只是一种实现方式，当然，如果你不喜欢这些函数，勇敢地去改变它们。This is just one way to do it, of course. If you don't like these functions, go ahead and change them.

来看看controls.cpp里面在做什么。Let's see what's inside controls.cpp.
<h1>实际的代码The actual code</h1>
我们需要几个变量。We'll need a few variables.
<pre class="brush: cpp">// position
glm::vec3 position = glm::vec3( 0, 0, 5 );
// horizontal angle : toward -Z
float horizontalAngle = 3.14f;
// vertical angle : 0, look at the horizon
float verticalAngle = 0.0f;
// Initial Field of View
float initialFoV = 45.0f;

float speed = 3.0f; // 3 units / second
float mouseSpeed = 0.005f;</pre>
FoV is the level of zoom. 80° = very wide angle, huge deformations. 60° - 45° : standard. 20° : big zoom.

首先通过输入重新计算位置，水平角度，竖直角度和视场角（FoV），从而计算出视图和投影矩阵。We will first recompute position, horizontalAngle, verticalAngle and FoV according to the inputs, and then compute the View and Projection matrices from position, horizontalAngle, verticalAngle and FoV.
<h2>方向Orientation</h2>
读取鼠标的位置是容易的：Reading the mouse position is easy :
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Get mouse position
int xpos, ypos;
glfwGetMousePos(&amp;xpos, &amp;ypos);</pre>
但是需要把光标放到屏幕的中心，否则它将会很快移到屏幕外，导致移不动它。but we have to take care to put the cursor back to the center of the screen, or it will soon go outside the window and you won't be able to move anymore.
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Reset mouse position for next frame
glfwSetMousePos(1024/2, 768/2);</pre>
注意：这段代码里假设了窗口的大小是1024*768，但这不是必须的，你也可以使用glfwGetWindowSize来设定想要的窗口大小。Notice that this code assumes that the window is 1024*768, which of course is not necessarily the case. You can use glfwGetWindowSize if you want, too.

计算观察角度：We can now compute our viewing angles :
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Compute new orientation
horizontalAngle += mouseSpeed * deltaTime * float(1024/2 - xpos );
verticalAngle   += mouseSpeed * deltaTime * float( 768/2 - ypos );</pre>
从右往左阅读这几行代码：Let's read this from right to left :
<ul>
	<li>1024/2 - xpos表示鼠标离窗口中心点的距离，这个值越大，转动的角度越大。1024/2 - xpos means : how far is the mouse from the center of the window ? The bigger this value, the more we want to turn.</li>
	<li>float(...)是转换为浮点数，使乘法顺利进行float(...) converts it to a floating-point number so that the multiplication goes well.</li>
	<li>mouseSpeed是用来加速或减慢旋转，可以按意愿调整或让用户选择。mouseSpeed is just there to speed up or slow down the rotations. Finetune this at will, or let the user choose it.</li>
	<li>+= : 如果你没有移动鼠标，1024/2-xpos的值为零，horizontalAngle+=0也没有改变horizontalAngle的值。如果你用"="替换，就需要每帧强制转回到原始的方向，这样不太方便。+= : If you didn't move the mouse, 1024/2-xpos will be 0, and horizontalAngle+=0 doesn't change horizontalAngle. If you had a "=" instead, you would be forced back to your original orientation each frame, which isn't good.</li>
</ul>
现在在世界坐标系下计算一个向量，即观察的方向。We can now compute a vector that represents, in World Space, the direction in which we're looking
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Direction : Spherical coordinates to Cartesian coordinates conversion
glm::vec3 direction(
    cos(verticalAngle) * sin(horizontalAngle),
    sin(verticalAngle),
    cos(verticalAngle) * cos(horizontalAngle)
);</pre>
这是一个标准的计算，如果你不了解余弦（cosine）和正弦（sinus），下面有一个简短的解释：This is a standard computation, but if you don't know about cosine and sinus, here's a short explanation :

<img class="alignnone whiteborder" title="Trigonometric circle" src="http://www.numericana.com/answer/trig.gif" alt="" width="150" height="150" />

上面的公式只是三维3D的归纳。The formula above is just the generalisation to 3D.

现在想计算“朝上”向量。“朝上”不一定总是朝向Y轴正方向：例如你俯视时，“朝上”向量实际上是水平方向的。这里有一个例子，有着相同位置，相同目标的相机，但是却有着不同的“朝上”方向。Now we want to compute the "up" vector reliably. Notice that "up" isn't always towards +Y : if you look down, for instance, the "up" vector will be in fact horizontal. Here is an example of to cameras with the same position, the same target, but a different up.

在本例中，唯一不变的是相机朝右的方向是水平的。验证方法是把手臂水平伸直，向上、下、任何方向去观察。接着定义“朝右”向量：因为是水平的，所以Y值为零，X和Z值就像上面数据一样，但是有90度或Pi/2弧度的旋转。In our case, the only constant is that the vector goes to the right of the camera is always horizontal. You can check this by putting your arm horizontal, and looking up, down, in any direction. So let's define the "right" vector : its Y coordinate is 0 since it's horizontal, and its X and Z coordinates are just like in the figure above, but with the angles rotated by 90°, or Pi/2 radians.
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Right vector
glm::vec3 right = glm::vec3(
    sin(horizontalAngle - 3.14f/2.0f),
    0,
    cos(horizontalAngle - 3.14f/2.0f)
);</pre>
我们有一个“朝右”向量和一个“方向”，或者说是“朝前”向量。而“朝上”向量是垂直于它们的。一个非常有用的数学工具可以让它们的联系变得简单：叉乘。we have a "right" vector and a "direction", or "front" vector. The "up" vector is a vector that is perpendicular to these two. A useful mathematical tool makes this very easy : the cross product.
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Up vector : perpendicular to both direction and right
glm::vec3 up = glm::cross( right, direction );</pre>
叉乘是在做什么呢，想知道非常简单。回忆第三课中讲到的右手定则。第一个向量是大拇指；第二个是食指；叉乘的结果就是中指。十分方便。To remember what the cross product does, it's very simple. Just recall the Right Hand Rule from Tutorial 3. The first vector is the thumb; the second is the index; and the result is the middle finger. It's very handy.
<h2>位置Position</h2>
这部分的代码十分明确。需要提的一点是，我用上/下/右/左键来替代方向键，因为在我的azerty键盘中，方向键实际代表zqsd。其实在qwerZ键盘中也不一样的，更不谈韩国键盘了。我甚至不知道韩国人民用的键盘是什么布局，但我猜想肯定很不一样。The code is pretty straightforward. By the way, I used the up/down/right/left keys instead of the awsd because on my azerty keyboard, awsd is actually zqsd. And it's also different with qwerZ keyboards, let alone korean keyboards. I don't even know what layout korean people have, but I guess it's also different.
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Move forward
if (glfwGetKey( GLFW_KEY_UP ) == GLFW_PRESS){
    position += direction * deltaTime * speed;
}
// Move backward
if (glfwGetKey( GLFW_KEY_DOWN ) == GLFW_PRESS){
    position -= direction * deltaTime * speed;
}
// Strafe right
if (glfwGetKey( GLFW_KEY_RIGHT ) == GLFW_PRESS){
    position += right * deltaTime * speed;
}
// Strafe left
if (glfwGetKey( GLFW_KEY_LEFT ) == GLFW_PRESS){
    position -= right * deltaTime * speed;
}</pre>
这里唯一需要注意的是deltaTime。你不想每帧偏离1单元，原因简短来说如下：The only special thing here is the deltaTime. You don't want to move from 1 unit each frame for a simple reason :
<ul>
	<li>如果你有一台运行快的电脑，每秒跑60帧，那么移动(60*速度单位)/秒If you have a fast computer, and you run at 60 fps, you'd move of 60*speed units in 1 second</li>
	<li>如果你有一台运行慢的电脑，每秒跑20帧，那么移动(20*速度单位)/秒If you have a slow computer, and you run at 20 fps, you'd move of 20*speed units in 1 second</li>
</ul>
有一个更好的电脑不是运行更快的必要条件，你需要通过“最后一帧的时间”或“时间增量（deltaTime）”来控制距离的比例。Since having a better computer is not an excuse for going faster, you have to scale the distance by the "time since the last frame", or "deltaTime".
<ul>
	<li>如果你有一台运行快的电脑，每秒跑60帧，那么移动(1/60*速度单位)/帧，即(1*速度)/秒。If you have a fast computer, and you run at 60 fps, you'd move of 1/60 * speed units in 1 frame, so 1*speed in 1 second.</li>
	<li>如果你有一台运行慢的电脑，每秒跑20帧，那么移动(1/20*速度单位)/帧，即(1*速度)/秒If you have a slow computer, and you run at 20 fps, you'd move of 1/20 * speed units in 1 second, so 1*speed in 1 second.</li>
</ul>
哪一种更好。deltaTime计算起来非常简单：which is much better. deltaTime is very simple to compute :
<pre class="brush: cpp">double currentTime = glfwGetTime();
float deltaTime = float(currentTime - lastTime);</pre>
<h2>Field Of View</h2>
更有趣的是，我们可以绑定鼠标，使它在视野中运动，因而可以小范围缩放：For fun, we can also bind the wheel of the mouse to the Field Of View, so that we can have a cheap zoom :
<pre class="brush: cpp">float FoV = initialFoV - 5 * glfwGetMouseWheel();</pre>
<h2>计算矩阵Computing the matrices</h2>
计算矩阵已经很明确了。使用几乎和前面一样的函数，但是是新的参数。Computing the matrices is now straightforward. We use the exact same functions than before, but with our new parameters.
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Projection matrix : 45° Field of View, 4:3 ratio, display range : 0.1 unit &lt;-&gt; 100 units
ProjectionMatrix = glm::perspective(FoV, 4.0f / 3.0f, 0.1f, 100.0f);
// Camera matrix
ViewMatrix       = glm::lookAt(
    position,           // Camera is here
    position+direction, // and looks here : at the same position, plus &quot;direction&quot;
    up                  // Head is up (set to 0,-1,0 to look upside-down)
);</pre>
<h1>结果Results</h1>
<a href="http://www.opengl-tutorial.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/moveanim.gif"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-372" title="moveanim" src="http://www.opengl-tutorial.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/moveanim.gif" alt="" width="206" height="159" /></a>
<h2>隐面消除Backface Culling</h2>
现在可以自由地移动鼠标，你会注意到，如果鼠标移动到立方体里面，仍然显示多边形。这看起来是显然的，但是实际上提供了一个优化的机会。而在一个常用应用中，你从来不会处于立方体内。Now that you can freely move around, you'll notice that if you go inside the cube, polygons are still displayed. This can seem obvious, but this remark actually opens an opportunity for optimisation. As a matter of fact, in a usual application, you are never _inside_ a cube.

有一个解决办法是让GPU检查摄像机在三角形的后面还是前面。如果在前面，显示三角形；如果在后面，也不在网格内，并且网格是封闭的，那么将有另一个三角形在它前面，但是没有人会注意到，除了一切都会变快：三角形数量平均少了两倍！The idea is to let the GPU check if the camera is behind, or in front of, the triangle. If it's in front, display the triangle; if it's behind, *and* the mesh is closed, *and* we're not inside the mesh, *then* there will be another triangle in front of it, and nobody will notice anything, except that everything will be faster : 2 times less triangles on average !

值得开心的是要验证这个很简单。GPU计算三角形的法向（用叉乘，记得吧？），然后检查这个法向是否朝向摄像机。The best thing is that it's very easy to check this. The GPU computes the normal of the triangle (using the cross product, remember ?) and checks whether this normal is oriented towards the camera or not.

不幸的是这样做有代价：三角形的方向是隐式的。这意味着如果你在缓冲区中交换两个顶点，可能结果会产生洞。但是一般来说，这值得额外的一点工作。经常，你需要在3D模型中点击“反转法向”（实际是交换两个顶点，从而反转法向方向），然后就一切正常了。This comes at a cost, unfortunately : the orientation of the triangle is implicit. This means that is you invert two vertices in your buffer, you'll probably end up with a hole. But it's generally worth the little additional work. Often, you just have to click "invert normals" in your 3D modeler (which will, in fact, invert vertices, and thus normals) and everything is just fine.

让隐面消除是很轻松的：Enabling backface culling is a breeze :
<pre class="brush: cpp">// Cull triangles which normal is not towards the camera
glEnable(GL_CULL_FACE);</pre>
<h1>练习Exercices</h1>
<ul>
	<li>限制verticalAngle以便你不能颠倒方向Restrict verticalAngle so that you can't go upside-down</li>
	<li>创建一个摄像机，使它绕着物体旋转 ( position = ObjectCenter + ( radius * cos(time), height, radius * sin(time) ) )；然后将半径/高度/时间的变化绑定到键盘/鼠标上。等等诸如此类的事情Create a camera that rotates around the object ( position = ObjectCenter + ( radius * cos(time), height, radius * sin(time) ) ); bind the radius/height/time to the keyboard/mouse, or whatever</li>
	<li>玩的开心！Have fun !</li>
</ul>